Guide to the North Carolina Mutual Life Insurance Company Archives, 1850, 1888-2000s and undated, bulk 1920-2008 RL.00936
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Printed Materials, 1903-2008 and undated; 1920s-1990s; 51 boxes
  - Publications by Other Organizations, 1914-2006 and undated
    - Non-NCM Serials
      - Ebony, 1955 (reprints); 1985; 2005 (Box 168)
      - Ebony, 1955 Sept.; 1959 Mar. (reprints), box size: 13x18 inches (Box OV37)
      - Ebony, 1963 May; 1966 June; 1967 Mar.-Apr.; 1969 May; 1971 Mar; 1973 Aug.-Sept., Dec., 5 folders; box size: 13x18 inches (Box OV37)
      - Fortune, 1974 Oct. (Box 168)
      - Gaffney Ledger (S.C.), 1928, July 12 (photocopied by NCM), box size: 20x24 inches (Box OV38)
        Was archived due to a front-page article (partial) of the indictment of a Dr. C. L. Norris, (Gaffney, South Carolina's sole African American physician), in connection with his medical examinations work for North Carolina Mutual's branch office.
      - Hotline and Unity News, 1963-1983, box size: 14x18 inches (Box OV36)
      - Humanities, 2006 May/June (Box 168)
      - Input, 1966 (Box 168)
      - Inside Track, 1987 Fall (Box 168)
      - The Insurance Examiner, 1939 Mar. (Box 168)
      - The Insurance Field, 1926 Aug. 6, box size: 14x18 inches (Box OV36)
      - The Insurance Leader, 1919-1920 (Box 169)
      - Intercollegiate Digest, 1935 Nov., 2 copies (Box 169)
      - Jet, 1983-2005 (Box 169)
      - The Journal of Negro History, 1962-1996, 8 folders (Box 169)
      - The Kappa-Alpha-Psi Journal, 1926-1929 (Box 169)
      - The Little Voice, 1927 July 9, box size: 20x24 inches (Box OV38)
      - Local History and Genealogy, 1948 (Box 169)
      - The Macon Courier, 1983 Feb. 15, box size: 20x24 inches (Box OV38)
      - The Message, 1951 Sept. (Box 169)
      - The Messenger, 1927 Mar., box size: 11x14 inches (Box OV9)
      - The Mouthpiece, 1925 Feb. (Box 169)
      - The Nation, 1952, Sept. 27 (Box 169)
      - The National Magazine of Commerce, 1935 Jan. (Box 169)
      - National Negro Digest, circa 1937 (Box 169)
      - The Nation-Wide Review, 1928 Sept. (Box 169)
      - The Negro History Bulletin, 1962-1975, 2 of 8 folders (Box 169)
      - The Negro History Bulletin, 1962-1975, 6 of 8 folders (Box 170)
      - Negro Progress in North Carolina, 1950-1964, 3 folders (Box 170)
      - The Negro Worker, 1944 July (Box 170)
      - The New York Stock Exchange Magazine, 2005 May/June (Box 170)
      - The News and Observer, 1992 June 17, box size: 20x24 inches (Box OV38)
      - Opportunity, 1923-1935 (Box 170)
      - Pageant, 1963 July (Box 170)
      - The Philadelphia Tribune, 1983 February 8, box size: 20x24 inches (Box OV38)
      - The Pilot, 1951-1954, 8 folders (Box 170)
      - The Pilot, 1955-1965, 17 folders (Box 171)
      - The Pilot, 1966-1978, 13 folders (Box 172)
      - Probe, 1961 April (Box 172)
      - The Quarterly Journal, 1940 October (Box 172)
      - The Radiator, 1922-1923, 4 folders (Box 172)
      - The Saturday Evening Post, 1945 Mar. 27 (Box 172)
      - Sepia, 1983 July (Box 172)
      - Survey Graphic, 1942 Nov. (Box 172)
      - Tar Heel Junior Historian, African American Life Edition, 1995 Fall (Box 172)
      - The Trumpet of Conscience, undated (Vol. 1, No. 2) (Box 172)
      - The Underwriters' Forum, 1947 Jan.-May (Box 172)
      - The Wayfarer, 1965 Fall (Box 172)
      - Weekly News Review Digest and Best's Insurance News, 1924-1940 (Box 172)
        Carries extensive handwritten annotations and lists.
      - The Saturday Evening Post, 1943 Mar. 27, box size: 11x14 inches (Box OV14)
      - Sentinel, 1983 Apr. 14, box size: 11x14 inches (Box OV14)
      - The Triangle Tribune, 1998 Oct. 11, NC Mutual 100th anniversary edition; box size: 14x18 inches (Box OV36)
      - Tribune supplement, 1966, and The Durham Morning Herald, 1973 Nov. 4, box size: 14x18 inches (Box OV36)
      - The Wall Street Journal, 1994 Sept. 27, box size: 20x24 inches (Box OV38)
      - Unidentified newspaper (Durham Negro Observer?), circa 1920 (photocopy), box size: 20x24 inches (Box OV38)
        Contains advertising for insurance companies, including North Carolina Mutual Life Insurance Company, and the society of the Royal Knights of King David, as well as an article on lynching and the response of the Charlotte News and Observer. Also featured are society comments, and notes on businesses, local events, and churches.
  - Other Printed Material
    Contains two oversize posters acquired by North Carolina Mutual staff.
    - A Picture History of the American Negro, (poster), circa 1960s (Oversize-folder 10)
      Consists of a large black-and-white poster measuring approximately 36x48 inches, displaying the history of Africans and African Americans in the United States from the 1700s to the 20th century. Includes small portraits and biographies of notable individuals: abolitionists, politicians, authors, artists, and civil rights leaders. Background paper color is ivory; fonts and portraits are in brown.
    - National African American leadership salutes the Million Man March, October 16, 1995, Washington, DC...Day of Atonement / Michael Brown, (poster), 1995 (Oversize-folder 11)
      Large poster consisting of a color collage of images of African American men; at its center is iconic image of slave with back turned to show scars. Mounted on foam core support, measuring 24 1/2 x 34 1/2 inches. Signature appears to be M.T. Row. Produced by Things Graphics and Fine Arts, Washington, DC.
  - Items Closed Pending Conservation
    Extremely brittle item; closed pending conservation treatment.
    - Large typed list of districts and offices with handwritten annotations, mounted on cardboard support, 1920s? (Oversize-box OV 54)
- Recordings, 1943-circa 1970s; 5 boxes and 19 film cans
  Series houses sound and moving image recordings spanning many decades and documenting milestones in North Carolina Mutual History. Formats include audiocassettes, audio tape reels, film reels, and videocassettes.
  Audiocassettes are few in number and include a set of home-study tapes on insurance practices.
  Subjects of films include a history of North Carolina Mutual; the history of "Black Wall Street" in Durham; the groundbreaking and dedication ceremonies for the current headquarters building on Chapel Hill Street in Durham; and advertisements and broadcasts about NC Mutual products and services. Titles of films listed have been taken from original canister or box labels. Many of these films were copied in digital format to DVD, around 2002 (see listings of digitized moving images in Digital Material Series).
  Original audiovisual recordings are closed to use. Access to these materials may require production of listening or viewing copies. Please contact Research Services before coming to use this collection.
  - Audio Recordings, 1962, 1963, 1987, and undated
    [Original audiovisual materials are closed to use. Use of these materials may require production of listening or viewing copies. Please contact Research Services before coming to use this collection.]
    - HS 328, Investments - audiocassette for home study created by Insurance Achievement, Inc., 1987, 5 cassettes (Box 175)
    - Radio commercials on audiotape reels, undated, 22 reels (Box 175-A)
      Primarily seems to consist of radio commercials on 3-, 4-, and 5-inch reels.
    - Unidentified audiotape reels, undated, 3 reels (Box 175-B)
      Unlabeled, 8" reels.
    - Adventures in Negro History, 1963 (Box 175-C)
      Set of 2 commercially produced record albums (LPs) with booklet, released in 1963 by Highlight Radio Productions, presented by Pepsi-Cola, directed by Fred Flowerday, and narrated by Jerry Blocker.
    - The Saxton Show, KTVM, FM 103.9, 1962 Feb. 15 (Box 175-C)
      Radio show featuring guests Asa Spaulding and H.J. Clement, 10.5" audio reel.
  - Films, 1948-1976 and undated
    Series of NCM-produced films and advertising spots, including a history of NCM created in 1948. Film footage is approximate. All but FILM 17 are reels of film; FILM 17 is an archival box housing multiple films.
    - Black Ambassador, Home and Abroad, circa 1976, 2550 feet (Film-reel 1)
      "Shipped to WRAL-TV...6/25/76." Memorex video tape, 2".
    - Hi band dub N.C. Mutual Founders' Day 29:19, 1970 October 24, 3200 feet (Film-reel 2)
      RCA video tape, 2".
    - Dubs of NC Mutual Founders Day, undated, 3200 feet (Film-reel 3)
      RCA, video tape, 2".
    - WTTW #47325 Spaulding Spots, circa 1964 (Film-reel 4)
      WTTW in Chicago. Three small reels inside 11.5" can.
    - Success Story, undated (Film-reel 5)
      "Missing most of title."
    - NC Mutual, 1966, 747 feet (Film-reel 6)
      Charles Crone Agency. Black and white 16mm film.
    - Dedication Ceremony, 1966, 1200 feet (Film-reel 7)
      16mm film.
    - Groundbreaking, circa 1965, 1200 feet (Film-reel 8)
      "Film and video tape division WTTW Chicago."
    - Success Story, 1948; 725 feet, bw, sound
      - 16mm original, bw, sound, 725 ft. (Box Fully Processed: 187, Film-reel RL00936-F16-0001)
      - Preservation digital copy (Digital-materials SET-0001, Video-file RL00936-F16-0001.mov)
    - NC Mutual Ads #1-4, Dangerfield, undated (Film-reel 10)
      Container houses 3.5" reel with one film; and one 4.75" reel with four films on it, according to labels. 16mm format.
    - NC Mutual, Charles Crone Assoc., undated, 500 feet (Film-reel 11)
      Has not been screened, but likely contains NCM commercials produced by Charles Crone Associates advertising agency; 16mm film.
    - NCM Dedication Ceremonies, 1966, 700 feet (Film-reel 12)
    - NC Mutual 'Success Story,' undated, 500 feet (Film-reel 13)
    - NC Mutual, circa 1966, 100 feet, 2 reels (Film-reel 14)
      "Humphrey 1966." WTTW kine negative original.
    - NC Mutual, 1966 April 15, 810 feet (Film-reel 15)
      WTTW kine negative original. Also on can: "Humphrey neg 1966." 16mm, sound.
    - The Quiet Road to Success, VTR #1, 29:30, WRAL-TV 5, Raleigh (Film-reel 16)
    - Tribute to Martin Luther King, January 14, 1972, 2:37: Producer: Clayton Weaver (Box FILM 17)
    - North Carolina Mutual, Jogger, 0:30, 28 May '81: Brand Edmonds Packett, WDBJ-TV7, Roanoke, 1981 (Box FILM 17)
    - NC Mutual Insurance, Jogger, 0:30, 10-17-80: WPTF-TV28, 1980 (Box FILM 17)
    - NC Mutual, NCMU-0130, 0:30, dub 9/3/81: WRAL-TV5, Raleigh, 1981 (Box FILM 17)
    - The Achiever, 0:30 commercial spot, color, undated, 7 copies (Box FILM 17)
    - Success Story, b/w, "mailed 1959 Oct. 12" (label on envelope), includes small sections that were removed from the enclosed film (Box FILM 17)
      [This film is in need of preservation. Please contact Research Services to use this material, as contents should be treated before being handled.]
    - Various film reels - commercials and other content (Box FILM 18)
    - Various film reels - commercials and other content, 19 film reels (Box FILM 19)
      Primarily consists of television commercials on 16 mm film.
  - Videocassettes, 1990s-1999 and undated
    Titles and dates are taken from original container labeling. Total running time (TRT) given when possible. Arranged in alphabetical order by title.
    - Antique Truck, undated, [U-Matic, TRT :30] (Box 175-A)
    - Community Mental Health and Health Care Reform, with Dr. Fred McCall Perez, a member of President Clinton's Health Care Task Force, 1990s, [VHS, TRT :30] (Box 176)
    - National Insurance Association (NIA), 1997 Atlanta, Howard Catching and Coretta Scott King, [VHS] (Box 176)
    - NIA 1997 Awards Banquet, [VHS] (Box 176)
    - NIA 1997 President's Banquet, J. Lowery, [VHS] (Box 176)
    - Ninety-Five Years of Sales and Service, 1993, [VHS] (Box 176)
    - NCM Centennial Celebration Documentary, 1999, [VHS] (Box 176)
    - NCM Christmas, 1992, [VHS] (Box 176)
    - NCM Employee Forum, 1999, [VHS] (Box 176, Box 189)
    - NCM: The First 100 Years, circa 1999, [VHS] (Box 176, Box 189)
    - NCM 94th Founders Day Program, 1992, [VHS] (Box 176)
    - NCM Life Insurance Show, 1988 May 24 (dubbed) (Box 189)
- Scrapbooks, 1912-1975; 6 boxes
  Varying in size and condition, these scrapbooks commemorate the history of North Carolina Mutual Life Insurance through clippings, photographs, memos, programs, and other items. Also found in the photographic material section in the Oversize Material Series are photo albums that also commemorate company personnel, conferences and other events, and milestones.
  [Scrapbooks are fragile; some are slated for further preservation treatment. Please contact Research Services before coming to use this material.]
  - Scrapbook 1, 1966, box size: 13x18 inches (Box OV40)
    Commemorating the dedication of new home office building, this scrapbook chiefly contains many pages of congratulatory messages in the form of letters and telegrams, many from notable officials, politicians, and businessmen.
  - Scrapbook 2, 1975, box size: 21x25 inches (Box OV41)
    History of NC Mutual from its beginnings to the 1970s. Almost completely made up of cut-outs from the company publication Whetstone.
  - Scrapbook 3, 1961-1967, box size: 23x29 inches (Box OV42)
    Contains newspaper clippings of NCM advertisements, along with a photograph, clippings of competitor's ads, and an event program. Approximately 25" x 17".
  - Scrapbook 4, 1920-1939, box size: 17x21 inches (Box OV43)
    Eighteen-page portfolio (approximately 13" x 16") belonging to calligrapher and illustrator Walter W. Micheaux. Micheaux was recognized as an expert penman and, after moving from South Carolina. in 1916, illustrated and hand-lettered the insurance policies, publicity, logos, and other material for NCM for over 20 years. Scrapbook contains many original examples of his work, as well as a 1928 clipping about him (with photo), and a small photo of him as an older man.
    [Extremely fragile. Slated for conservation treatment. Please consult with a reference archivist before using.]
  - Scrapbook 5, 1912, 1943-1963, 1972 and undated, box size: 12x16 inches (Box OV47)
    The majority of the contents of this scrapbook are dedicated to the launching of the S.S. Merrick in honor of John Merrick on July 11, 1943. Also includes a specially-bound edition of the Whetstone edition honoring NCM's 50th anniversary, as well as various newspaper clippings relating to individuals and other entities connected to NCM. Other items laid in to the scrapbook are copies of a letter and photo from President John F. Kennedy, a 1946 Whetstone honoring John Merrick, and an unidentified Atlantic City vacation photograph of NC Mutual staff, circa 1940s.
  - Scrapbook 6, 1936-1941 (Box 177)
    Scrapbook of newspaper clippings belonging to J.L. Wheeler, NCM Agency Director of the Southern Region.
  - NCM Annual Meeting, 1991-2003 (Box 197)
    Contains correspondence, photographs, and invitations. Also includes photographs from NCM Annual Meeting Spouse Programs.
  - President's Club Convention, 1990 (Box 197)
    Includes photographs from the 1990 meeting in San Francisco, CA.
  - President's Club Convention, 2001 (Box 197)
    Includes photographs and invitations.
- Social Groups and Events, 1922-1992 and undated; 1 box
  Files relate to social clubs and events for North Carolina Mutual employees. The groups that are chronicled in these files include the NCM Glee Club and the Tuesday Morning Study Group, a self-improvement group composed chiefly of the wives of NCM administrators that met to read about and discuss political, social and cultural topics of the day. Materials on the latter make up the majority of these items.
  - Tuesday Morning Study Club: Minutes, 1962-1977, 2 folders (Box 178)
  - Tuesday Morning Study Club: Correspondence and memorabilia, 1966-1977 (Box 178)
  - Tuesday Morning Study Club: Agendas and readings, 1973-1976 (Box 178)
  - Tuesday Morning Study Club: Materials on meeting topic, "The Great Transition," 1977 (Box 178)
    "The Great Transition" theme taken up by the NCM social group, the Tuesday Morning Study Club, may refer to the term as used by Kenneth Boulding, social reformer, economist, educator, and systems scientist, in 1965, to mean a pivotal moment in social science and human society as it transitions from the 20th to the 21st century.
  - Tuesday Morning Study Club: "The Great Transition," three cassettes for study meeting, circa 1977 (Box 175)
    Access Restrictions
    Original audiovisual recordings are closed to use. Use of these materials may require production of listening or viewing copies. Please contact Research Services before coming to use this collection.
  - Greetings, announcements, and ads, 1924-1927 (Box 178)
  - Glee Club history and programs, 1922 and undated (Box 178)
  - "Hayti Lived Before" (stage play, circa 1992), and the June 28, 1952 issue of The Nation (Box 178)